Translation/Subtitle: jls001999 (jls001999@gmail.com)
Review/Proofreading: coralsundy (coralsundy@gmail.com)
(Paid by coralsundy for the translation, personal use only)
Shunkin Monogatari / The Story of Shunkin (1954)
The time of the old school era,
around the end of the Tokugawa government
In Osaka,
There is a place called Doshomachi
where only Medicinal Liquor Wholesaler
This is one of Osaka’s oldest and most historic neighborhoods.
At that time, in May of the third year
of Keio, on the day of the Tango Festival,
The Prime Minister of Goshu,
Hinoya Kahei, accompanied by his heir, Sasuke, traveled all the way from Goshu.
This is one of the oldest establishments Medicinal Liquor Wholesaler in Doshomachi
Sasuke was to be sent as an apprentice to the shop of Mozuya Yasudaimon,
a well-known and long-established pharmaceutical wholesaler in Doshomachi, to learn the ropes of the business
Oh Koji-sama
This is the second lady,Okoto from the Ito clan
You go to lessons for shamisen or okoto
The protagonist of this story,
Okoto (later known as Shunkin),
She lost both of her eyes in a
sudden incident several years ago
Since then, She has been living a pitiful life outside the temple grounds, diligently practicing the shamisen
Sasuke?
Thinking back, the story of love and desire permeated by the mysterious beauty of Sasuke and Okoto,
began at this very moment of their first meeting
And so, eight years later, the world changed to the Meiji era of modernization and civilization, and one day...
One day,
Sasuke's father, Kahei, came to visit the mozuya from Hinourazawa in Goshu
Sasuke?
Dad.
It seems you look fine.
Are you well-liked by everyone?
Yes.
I haven't even introduced myself to your master yet, so I feel bad speaking to you
I'll take the permission first.
I'll talk to you later.
I get it.
Shinei-san?
It seems like the supply from the Ibuki area is poor this year
Yeah....
All the medicinal herbs will do their worst in this summer's Sidel
It seems our master's plan worked.
They are here.
Oh? Well, well, I appreciate your respect.
Thanks.
Are you and everyone else safe?
I am deeply grateful for that.
I received and for being able to meet Sasuke.
I'd appreciate for that.
He's doing well too
Hey, hey,
Tell Sasuke that his dad is here
I get it.
Sasuke.
Is Sasuke here?
What can I do for you?
Koi-san is about to go for practice
Koi
Tell her not to go for practice today.
Today his dad is here, so...
I get it.
what your dad says is absolutely right,
I'll have to ask you to take over
It's been a while, so I'm sure he has a lot to talk with his son
Oh yeah
Okay then, if you know someone like Sasuke who's used to being led around,
If you know anyone who never complains, please bring him here.
Who's there?
Koi-san
Who's there? Hurry up!
I get it.
Sasuke?
Let us get by
Koi-san has arrived.
The master said she should take the day off today.
Would you like me to take her place?
How stupid
I don't know what to say to Koi-san
I'll go
Sorry for making you wait.
Sasuke?
Yes
What a beautiful.
She's really grown up.
Hey
I told you guys that Sasuke should take a break.
But Koi-san....
No one listens to my orders.
Master
Please be kind to her—she can't see.
Hinode-san
He's very picky, and if he likes her, he'll stick with her
I took Sasuke in to help him become a full-fledged merchant.
I don't think it's a good idea for him to have a relationship with her.
Osshuhan  took a break today?
She's sick today
That's right.
It seems she's caught a cold today,
but she'll still come and watch your lesson
She's done
Sorry to keep you waiting
Goodbye,Goodbye,
Koi-san
Osshuhan is sick today, but I'll teach you today
Try to play once.
Sasuke?
I'll go
Koi
Wait
Aren't you going to take my lessons?
Koi
I know you're very skilled in our lesson
But Osshuhan asked me to give you some training, so...
Sasuke
Koi-san! Just wait!
Koshi-san!
Teacher
Cut it out.
I know Mozuya is quite something
But, well, I am a woman who used to work at the Imperial Palace
I don't deserve to be made fun of by you.
If you can't accept my training,
then never come here again
Master
This is a battlefield!
What are you talking about?
But Master
I told you I practice Koi.
First of all, with your skills you can no longer teach Koi-san.
So what?
Do you think I'm less skilled than Koi?
Don't say that now!
It's time for you to go for training
Master
Shut up
I told you to go, so you should go!
Even at that age, she's still a woman's girl
Koi-san
Let's have our lesson
Yes
Sasuke?
I feel cold
It's cold and snowy
It might start snowing
Sasuke?
Yes
Am I arrogant?
What?
Am I arrogant that much?
I don't think so
You didn't have to care what she said.
Please forget what she said
Master spoils her way too much
Even in Osaka, his training is tough
Among the disciples was Ito Han, who had an experience as a Kengyo (a Buddhist school teacher)
Why does Master pamper her so much?
I've known that girl since she was young
She had a reputation for being good at it.
If she hadn't been blinded,
she would have been great
I feel sorry for her
It's a shame that a girl who was praised for being skillful was born with such talent
No, even now she's neat and tidy,
So, do you treat her differently?
You are stupid.
I am blind.
I don't understand what's so beautiful about her.
What I'm in love with is her skill and natural talent
She is the most talented of my students.
How about me?
I think if I were beautiful, you would treat me differently.
If I were prettier.....
What?
Are you jealous of her?
You can see.
KOI and I can't see.
Don't you think you are happy?
Seriously, all because my eyes are open
I can't help but look at Koi's beautiful face,
I'd rather go blind.
Fine, you idiot
What are you talking about?
KOI is still young.
Try to put yourself in her shoes.
Try being in her position for once
It's tough to be young and blind.
People who can see can't understand how she feels.
Oh! Koi-san !
Did you get hurt?
Koi-san
have you been watching this whole time?
No, I was doing some work in the storehouse
No!
You were secretly watching and other people didn't know about?
But what?
I'm asking if you just watched without telling me!
I'm sorry...
Idiot!
Koi-san
I'm so sorry
Please forgive me....
Koi-san.
Hold on
Don't touch me!
Leave me alone.
Koi-san,I'm so sorry
Please forgive me....
Please forgive me....Koi-san
Koi-san.
Oh, it's cold!
It's going to snow quite a bit, isn't it?
What happened to your hand?
Hmm? No, nothing.
I see
Listen, Koi-san
Master says the same thing
What?
about your marriage arrangements
I talked it over with him a lot.
How about getting married with Sasuke?
Sasuke knows about you well
For Koi-san
Mom
Sasuke is our servant, he belongs to our master, right?
No matter how I am blind
I have no intention of marrying him.
But Koi-san
besides Sasuke, who else will take care of you for the rest of your life?
Sasuke will take care of me for the rest of my life just like this?
I know how you feel...
but no matter how disabled or wealthy I am
I don't want you guys to make fun of me.
I will never, ever make fun of Koi-san in my life
I have no intention of undergoing training anymore.
I do not take lessons from the master.
Koi-san.
My master are Koto and shamisen.
I will continue making music for the rest of my life.
Thank you for the meal.
I want a refill.
Hold on.
Bring this
Katsudon?
Well, what's going on?
That's strange
I wonder if a ghost has attached itself to you.
Madam?
You don't need to laugh.
Koi-san?
He is in the drying area.
Isn't that Sasuke Sasuke?
Dad?
What do you do in the middle of the night?
Is that your shamisen?
Yes.
I've been saving up my wages and tips
It's too cold to talk here.
What exactly are you here?
You came here for training.
Aren't you a servant here for generations?
You didn't come here to study musicians.
Have you ever thought about that?
Sorry, sorry
No matter how many shamisens you buy, I will break them just like this.
You get it?
So?
It’s inconvenient that Sasuke is giving shamisen lessons.
I told him to practice in the warehouse.
He said People who are blind are always in complete darkness like this
So he imagine Koi-san is also playing in the dark
He's so happy to know that he's also part of the same dark world
He said that it was fun.
He is trying hard to get into Koi-san's good graces.
Mom.
what?
I want to know how well he could play.
You are stupid.
There is no way he can play the shamisen well.
I believe he can play well.
That sounds interesting. Let's go ahead and ask about it.
I'll call him.
Omiyan.
Sasuke?
Come here.
Please try tuning the shamisen and playing it once.
I will.
Make the sound heavier.
Turn up the volume on number 3.
Here you go.
Start.
Hold on.
You were playing the song "Snow" on the balcony, weren't you?
Yes.
Play it.
Here you go.
I wonder when he took his shamisen lesson.
Amazing.
Mom, what do you think?
It is truly amazing to be so passionate about something.
Hey.
I'm sorry for using something that is precious to you.
Never mind.
More than that,
If you like the shamisen, why not take some lessons?
I am asking the manager to ensure that you do not do any work at the shop.
Then,I will teach you the shamisen.
Koi-san.
You shall become my student.
Koi-san....
Please.
koto and Sasuke,They formally entered into a master-disciple relationship.
At first, those around her thought it was just a momentary whim of hers
Or They thought she was doing it just for fun.
The enthusiasm of the two, especially the intensity of Okoto's practice
She mentored him strictly.
No!
Did I teach you that way?
I’m sorry.
It's not!
Sorry.
I get it.
Ready?
Don’t play like that!
Sasuke!
Why would something like that be so difficult?
Why can't you play something this simple?
I'm sorry
Please.
Get ready.
You idiot!
Why can't you play something this simple?
How many times do you have to play it before you can remember it?!
I'm so sorry... I'm so sorry...
You lack the skills.
Stay up all night until you can play it.
Yes.
Keep going.
Yes,that's it.
And so, Sasuke gave up on becoming a merchant.
He entered the world of music.
Perhaps This performance captivated him.
whether it was for the sake of  Okoto, for his own sake,
He didn't understand who this music training was for.
Here it is.
There.
Thank you for going out of your way to come here for Sasuke.
I am very grateful for that.
Don't mention it.
I feel bad for asking you to take your son
away to the mock hall for my daughter for music.
What are you talking about?
That sort of thing is not the way to repay the kindness I have received.
Sasuke must be very pleased that he can now choose his own path together with his beloved
Well, hearing you say that makes me feel a little more at ease
It's been a while since we last met, but I'm sure Koi-san has improved even more
Her mentor treats her as very special.
Oh yeah.
Today will be a celebration for Her mentor.
At the celebration, he gave her a special name.
Did he give her a name?
What a nice!
Oh my, what an honorable
I wonder what it is
Ohira!
No!
Come on!
My hunch was right.
I hear that Koi-san is getting a name.
Koi-san?
Are you sure?
I've been blessed with a fine heir, Koi
I have no regrets about when I'll die
When I die, feel free to put up your sign.
Koi-san.
I am so grateful.
You received the character "Haru" from your master and were given the name Shunkin.
Thank you for naming me Shunkin
Hold on.
Isn't that out of order?
I don't know how important
Koi-chan is to you, but...
I have been training in for my master for seven years
So, I guess I'm just a geek like this
I suppose you wouldn't like me,
but I've served my master and I've worked as a servant,
and I don't know what you think of me, but I...
Even so, I consider myself to be on your side
You're drunk, aren't you?
What kind of thing do you say in front of other people?
I am sober.
I had been holding back from getting married and leaving home for a long time.
For seven years, I endured while you tested me, all the while hoping to receive a name from you.
For today's celebration, I thought I would be given a name.
I think it's terrible to mention a name to Koi-san before me.
No matter how much Koi-san said she was cute and sharp, that was just too much, too much
How many times do I have to tell you, you idiot?
Koi-san has the ability to deserve it
Therefore, I gave her my name.
No,
I won't lose to koi-san
I'll compare her anytime
Shall we do it right now?
Stop saying embarrassing things.
This is for our sake.
I am nothing but a fool.
Yeah, thanks to koi's scary faces
Stop it.
What are you doing?
You have an arrogant look on your face.
If you put up a sign, I'll put up a sign too.
Just bring it on!
I will compete with you on a technical level.
You don't need to compete with her.
Please stop saying terrible things to her.
You are a coward.
You are truly a fool.
You fell in love with a blind person—you really are a fool.
You bastard!
What?
I cannot stand being told things like that.
What's the hell?
Oei
Hey.
What's going on with you?
Let's stop using violence.
Koi-san.
Shall we go?
Wait, idiot!
Hey, what's the hell!
You are nothing but a servant.
Wat.
Koi-san.
What's wrong?
Sasuke.
Are you in a bad mood?
You have a fever!
Sasuke
Koi-san.
Are you okay?
You've never seen the play "Senbonzakura Kitsune Tadanobu no Michiyuki," have you?
I saw that play when I was seven
, and I could still see,
and I was just a person who loved the play,
and a loyal person who would even
go so far as to help a farming family
I thought it would be fine even if it was a fox, neither human nor animal
I will change your towel.
Oh, that's fine
You know what?
No matter what Oei says,
don't worry about it.
It doesn't bother me at all
But she's really that rude to Koi-san
Me?
I don't think anything of Oei at all.
You know what?
No matter what anyone says, you have to work hard at your play.
Please get better than me soon.
I cannot do such a thing.
You can do it.
You are a man.
I can't...
I want you to surpass me.
I'm sure you will be good, right?
Okay?
Yes
Oh yeah.
That's enough
You are sweating a lot.
Really?
Oh it's cold.
I'm sorry. Let's change it.
It's okay, it's okay.
My back.
It's dazzling.
Is it on fire?
Yes
It's dazzling.
Koi-san.
Goryo is here
My mom?
Yes.
I'll bring her.
Good morning
I'm coming.
Koi-san
Stop singing.
Everyone is very worried about our master's illness
But apparently, You're more worried about Koi-san than about his illness, aren't you?
What?
We met at a café by the river in the west.
There was a woman in a yukata tied with a cute obi.
Stop singing.
There are good things and bad things
You all have a very good reputation in this Doshomachi area
Koi-san might give birth to a child.
No matter what she does with that body
Sasuke-don,
Sasuke-don,you know right?
You know who got her pregnant, don't you?
She's not that kind of person
She's not the kind of person to say such pointless things
Why is her belly big?
Shut up.
What's wrong?
Stop badmouthing her.
Tell me.
Who got you pregnant?
Your father is very worried and is thinking about it a great deal.
That is the reason his health is poor.
I feel terrible about it....
Well, just you can me.
I can't tell.
We promised not to say anything for now
Did you make a promise?
Koi-san.
Is that man Sasuke?
If that is the case, I would be very relieved.
Even your father can say he'd be okay with him becoming his son-in-law if it's Sasuke
I can't tell.
Mom, please don't ask me anything anymore
But what do you think will become of the baby that's born?
He doesn't have a father.
We do not raise children of unknown origin at Mozuya
The Skylark.
Mom, do you remember Hibari well?
She lost her sight
That was the last bird I saw.
It was the last time everyone in the world would drink
The bird was taking flight into the vast sky, using both of its wings.
I'll keep watching you forever, until you get so small you can no longer see you
My eyes were still open back then, I could still see
I wish I could see....
You don't need to say anything more.
Hey everyone, we'll be there soon.
Tonight we'll visit the local training room and practice
Osshuhan
Please do a good job.
Keep going.
It hurts me.
What's wrong?
What a crazy guy!
No matter how beautiful a woman is, it’s pointless if she can’t see.
I think blind women are wonderful.
Her face and her figure....
She can't see, hahahaha
It doesn't matter, it doesn't matter, just fall for it again
Get up,young master.
It is rude to sleep there.
No one will notice that.
Here we go.
The baby was born thanks to masters.
but she apparently died shortly afterward
Meanwhile, the traditional Mozuya shop,
which adheres to old-fashioned business practices, is increasingly
struggling to cope with the growing popularity of Western medicines
Eventually, grieving the passing of master.
He left home and set up a shop on Yodoyabashi Street,
displaying the Mozuya Shunkin sign, and began her new life together
The young Minoya master of a wholesale shop in Tosabori
That was also when Ritaro became an apprentice.
It was obvious to everyone that the young master who had just joined the school was interested in the master.
Ready?
Chiriririri-sunsunsun
Tsuntsntun-chinjan
That said,
The daily lives of these two were enough to pique the curiosity of anyone
Please stand up.
When she takes a bath, he changes her skincare products
From getting dressed and
putting on makeup to taking care of her.
Serving dishes 3 times a day.
He looked after her until she fell asleep.
no one was allowed to do anything for her.
only Sasuke-sama was permitted to perform these duties
It was truly a mysterious, enigmatic, yet beautiful relationship between the two of them
No, no, no, that's not it.
That's not what I'm asking
I mean....
So, how are you two going to take a break?
Osshuhan  is taking a break by herself.
Alone? And what about Sasuke-han?
Sasuke-han is on the second floor of the practice room
I see.
But.....
She likes him very much....
Don't say like that.
I can't tell anymore.
Never mind
How has she been lately?
She got naked in the bath.
She puts both her legs in this position, then puts her beast in Sasuke
In other words, it's like this, like this
What a sexy!
Please don't let your imagination run wild.
Yes! there is!
I found something good way.
What?
Sumiyoshi'person said like that.
Yeah.
You need to use your head more.
To Housewarming celebration
I have a good idea for that moment.
What?
Dantsuku?
Good!
This is a very good opportunity.
Dad.
Hey Master.
Take a look at that
Dad...
I brought her here as an apprentice knowing that the training would be strict
But surely there's no way someone would beat another person as punishment just because she's slow at learning the shamisen?
This girl, despite her appearance, is a trainee geisha whose face is her selling point and her business
You're the one who damaged our product.
What are you going to do about it?
Dad.
Shut up.
A husband is responsible for his wife's actions.
Yeah, isn't that right?
Yeah, that's right
Yeah of course
It's not true.
He is an apprentice
What?
You idiot.
You should have said that beforehand.
Are you an apprentice?
Hold on.
Well, for today we just have to stick with this
Just take it
Um.
I'm so sorry for causing you so much worry
Sasuke.
Please pay him back for the amount he covered for you.
You don't need to do that.
If I intended to get it back, I wouldn't have done it in the first place.
I was just worried about you
Please understand that.
How much was it?
No, it wasn't that much
It was only 5 Ryo.
but I can't accept something like this
I have a favor to ask of you.
What is that?
Well, the construction of our villa in Sumiyoshi is finally finished, and so
I'd love to invite you to my housewarming party
That's good.
Please come.
Actually,
It seems many people want to hear you play.
So please.
You are mean.
Why did you hear her performance before mine?
The order doesn't matter.
Well, that's fine, but instead of the order, I will give you a generous monetary gift.
I don't need that.
I didn't know that today's party was for her.
Please don't get so angry.
Have a drink.
It's her turn next.
I can't wait for her performance.
This name is truly wonderful.
A bush warbler comes to the hill and sings—or weeps.
A scene in a valley on a snowy day.
The tears are frozen.
The tears are frozen....
Look at them.
your face is disgusting
Oh I see.
He really likes eccentric people.
Thank you for your work.
Please show them to that table over there.
Please come with me.
Please sit over there.
Osshuhan ...
If I need anything, I will call you.
Enjoy your meal.
Thank you very much.
Please come this way.
Everyone was captivated by your performance.
That is a new composition of hers, isn't it?
I'm still not happy with it.
That was a truly wonderful performance.
I'm telling you the truth
Nao-chan
To tell you one more thing
I.....
You should be considerate of me.
This drink is chilled, isn't it?
I'm so sorry
I didn't notice that.
Wait a min.
Take your time.
Osshuhan
Who understood how I felt?
So I....
Minoya...
I am your master?
What are you talking about? In this
field, there are no masters or disciples
You have cute hands.
What are you doing?
Get your hands off of me!
No...
It hurts....
Damn it.
I’m sorry.
Sasuke!
Osshuhan
Is everything alright?
What happened?
Master! Master!
Master!
Who?
I'm sure you'll be satisfied
What?!
I was made to look like a complete fool in Manza.
So do I.
I want to get back at them.
Poor man.
I see.
Well then, I'd like to show you too, looking forward to it
Damn it.
Sasuke.
Yes.
Osshuhan
What's happening?
Don't look at me.
Don't look at my face.
I won't see.
Please tell me what happened?
Oh, what did it?
My face...my face....
Osshuhan
Someone please come,boss, someone, hurry, hurry
Hey
Someone hurry to come.
I'm coming.
What's happening?
Please call a doctor right away.
Oh my god.
Hurry up.
I will
Koi-san
Seriously, enough is enough
No matter how many times he comes... I... I can't do anything.
It can't be helped.
When you think about it, it was a pretty serious crime
I never intended to do anything
You look completely unconcerned, as if it were none of your business.
Wakabon.
No no!
This!
I have to leave early. Please excuse me.
Let's go home together.
Excuse me.
Sasuke.
what were they laughing at?
They were talking about my face, right?
Don't say like that.
Didn't you see his face back then?
Huh? You did, didn't you?
If you did, then tell me honestly that you saw my face
Osshuhan.
You keep asking the same thing over and over again.
I was told not to look, not to look
Yes, That is how she was.
I feel sorry for Sasuke, who doesn't seem to be doing as instructed
I have never once disobeyed your orders.
Osshuhan.
I know, I know,
but if this bandage comes off,
I won't be able to show this face to you, no matter what
I don't want.
Sasuke, don't look at my face.
Don't look at my terrible face.
Good morning.
Hey! Osshuhan.
Thank you for coming.
Hey,You know what?
I hear she is going to wear a bandage today.
Oh really! Today?
I wonder what her face looks like right now.
Yeah.
Well then,I'm off.
If this bandage comes off a
I don't care about anyone else, but I don't want you to look at my face.
I don't want.
Sasuke.
I am going through a very hard time.
Don't look! Don't look at my face,
Please never look at my face again for the rest of your life.
Come back soon!
Oh yeah, I forgot.
Okimi.
Please buy some needles.
You will experience pain after the bandage is removed for two or three days.
Please take care of her.
I understand
I'll prepare the medicine for you right away,
Then.
Thank you for your hard work.
I'm going to go get that medicine
Sasuke
Yes.
what are you doing!
where are you?
I'm here.
what's wrong?
I'm here
Where are you?
I'm here.
Sasuke,What's wrong?
Where are you?
Osshuhan.
Sasuke
What did you do?
Osshuhan.
Sasuke has gone blind
Sasuke can't see?
Sasuke
Is that true?
Yes.
I will never be able to see the scenery for the rest of my life.
Even though an intruder snuck in that night, I was unable to help.
I cannot get away with this alone; I hope that punishment will befall me
I prayed to the spirits of the deceased morning and evening
Thanks to that, my vision gradually became blurry,
I am in the same situation as you now.
The wish I made while in the darkness has been granted.
I am very grateful for that.
Osshuhan
My only concern is that you am quite blind,
so I apologize in advance for any inconvenience this may cause you regarding your order
I'll do my best to get used to it quickly
but please continue to let Sasuke take care of his personal needs all by himself, just like before
Please
Sasuke.
Are you not in pain?
Eh?
Was it really painful?
Yes...
No...No....
To be honest...
I don't want you to see my face like this
I don't want to show it
That was the only thing I was thinking about.
It was truly agonizing—I felt like I was dying.
I am truly grateful that you decided to look it.
I am truly grateful.
Sasuke.
I'm so happy
Thank you very much.
This joy outweighs the loss of both my eyes.
I don't know who poured boiling water on you.
If you don't want me to see the scar on your face, I simply won't look at it.
If even I become blind, I won't be able to see anything
As darkness gradually fades and the underworld narrows,
All I see before my eyes now is your beautiful face from before.
Sasuke.
Yes,Osshuhan.
Let's be alone together forever and ever
Osshuhan.
Sasuke.
Yes.
Koi-san.
This is what I have said
It was 6,7 years after these events that I became a disciple of Shunkin-sama.
Your performance is wonderful.
What's your name?
I'm Oteru.
How old are you?
I'm 9.
9.
I see.
If my child were alive, he would be nine years old.
Yes.
I find myself wishing I had children right now.
Osshuhan.
He was my first child.
Sasuke.
Where is that child's grave?
The child's grave was located in the Hinoya family cemetery in Hinoura, Goshu.
It was later revealed that the visit to the grave was arranged
after consultation between the previous head of Mozuya and Hinoya
In other words, Hinoya had secretly prepared
a way to introduce his grandchild to someone
Your glasses.
THE END